So now let's start. I'm using Isabelle as a demo, as a quick demo of recursion on lists.
So I will just, I did the same thing. So I will say theory, list, recursion, and then that
imports, main, begin, end. And I'll just do the same two examples that I did there
on pen and paper to show you, okay? So the first function was sum.
So append function sum. So the way you write functions, recursive functions in Isabelle,
the easiest way to do that is by doing this fun command, right? So sum and then the signature.
And then we'll just do an add list and returns an add. So sum of the empty list equals zero.
And sum of the non-empty list equals the first element plus sum of the rest of that list, okay?
So as you can see here, let me just say a few points. So Isabelle actually was able to show
that this function terminates. And when it did show that it did show that it terminates,
it produced two theorems that you can use improves again later on. So those theorems are,
for any recursive function, you have these functions, simps. So for example, in our case here, it's
sum. So sum.simps. So these are the two theorems that you can use to prove thanks about sum, okay?
Also, there is another important tool in Isabelle, which is value. So this value command
helps you to evaluate any function program that you write, any executable function program
that you write in Isabelle. So for example, here, if I write sum of one, two, and three,
this is six. So it evaluated it. Two, then we have three there. So that's also an important
thing that I wanted to say. So also, before I finish that, these functions are shown to be
terminated based on the fact that in every recursive call, you call that same function
on a smaller argument. So here, you call it, if, for example, you call sum on a smaller argument,
x. So smaller in any sense that you define. You basically have to define in your head,
have to define some notion of measure of how big your argument is, and then that measure has
to be decreasing with every recursive call. So for example, if you take the length as the measure,
then here, the length of the recursive call is one minus the length of the previous call.
So let's do another function. So the other one was append, right? So I'll just do append,
and that should take any list and any other list and return a list of the same type. And then I
say append, for example, we said that it would be recursive on the first argument. So if the
first argument is empty, then it should just return the second argument. And is non-empty,
then append it to the list that results from appending the rest of x's with y's.
That's, again, a recursive function. And again, it reduced append simps. And you can also evaluate it.
So let's say append to empty lists. So here, we cannot evaluate it. Why? Because
evaluation only happens to types whose elements are finite in size. So here, we don't know what
the type alpha is, because as we wrote here, this is an alpha. So we don't know what kind
of lists those are. If we change this to an add, then it terminates. And then it evaluates it and
shows you that it's an empty list. An alternative thing is to just say evaluate it on a list,
but then you say what is the type of the list. Then again, that also gives you the empty list.
And then, for example, if I just say 1, 2, then you have a list of 1, 2. And then here,
the second list has 34. Then it's like that. But if you have a 3 and 4, then it's also like that.
So it works as expected. So let me just do another function. Let's say maximum. So maximum in a list.
So that, again, I'll just do it for natural numbers. So you can take a natural number list
and return an add. And that's an interesting function, because for the empty case,
you're basically returning an arbitrary maximum, right? So I would just say the maximum of the
empty one is 0, because that's going to be smaller than any maximum of any other list.
And then for the non-empty case, I'm going to return the following. And let me just show you
that as well. Easable. How to do that? So maximum empty list is the following. So if x is greater
than or equal max list of x's, then we return x. Otherwise, we return max list x's. So that's one
way to define it. But there's also another function. So there's also another function in
Isabelle. Let me just show you an alternative definition. So here, I'll just call this max
list prime. And then, so in Isabelle, there is a function. Let me just show you how you
search for functions as well. So I want to search for a function that computes a maximum of two
given natural numbers. So I would say instead of find theorems, I would say find theorems.
And then I will try and guess what theorem would this function satisfy. And based on that,
I will get the theorems that have similar functions or a function that computes the max.
And then I can use that. So for example, we can say, okay, we want the function f,
such that if you give it two arguments, x and y, it has to be greater than x, and it also has to be
greater than y. So let's see. So we already have found that. And then you can keep
refining these search queries. So here, for example, this is the function that satisfies
what we want. So it's called max with a small m. So as you can see, so max is bigger than a.
And let me just make sure that it's also bigger than b. So we also say that. And then it's the
same. It returns the same thing. So max. So instead of saying if and else, this if and else big
thing, we just return max of x and max list of x's. Yeah, sorry, that should be a prime
because that's an alternative definition. And another way also to define max,
I'm trying to introduce you to as many as much as a validation as possible.
Maybe not this one. Another thing, another interesting construct in Isabelle that's relevant
here is the let construct. So instead of if and else, you just say let
just call this m equals, this is the recursive calls. I'll just say let m equals max list of
x's. Instead of calling max list twice, you just say if x is greater than or equal to m, then x
else return the same m. Okay, so that makes the code a bit cleaner than the first variant.
So let's try and evaluate max list. So let's say max list of one, two, three. So here we have three
and then four in the beginning and four in the middle and five next to the four. So then as
you can see, it works. And again, max simps are basically the definition, max list simps
are basically the definition of the equation, the equations that define max. And you can use
those to define, to prove theorems are max, which is what I will discuss in the next video.